TRAVIS JOSEPH KESSLER

University of Massachusetts Lowell One University Avenue, Lowell, MA 01854 travis.j.kessler@gmail.com, (978) 201-7710

Graduate student with more than 4 years of experience in academic research and open source software development. Confident in directing teammates and students as a project manager and teaching assistant. Capable of communicating across numerous scientific, engineering and business disciplines. Achievements include developing machine learning models to predict molecular properties with 34% more accuracy than historical average. Skilled in applied machine learning, data mining/pipelining, statistics, and software engineering development/management.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Software Languages

- * Python, C, C++
- * Javascript, HTML, CSS
- * SQL/NoSQL
- * Bash/Shell

Software Tools

- * TensorFlow, Keras
- * PyTorch, Scikit-Learn
- * MongoDB
- * Git, SVN

Software Environments

- * Azure Web Services
- * Amazon Web Services
- * Windows Server 2012+
- * Linux (Headless, GUI)

Working Environments

- * AGILE/SCRUM
- * DevOps Lifecycle
- * Kanban Organization
- * MRPT DoJ Clearance

EDUCATION

PhD Computer Engineering – GPA 3.93

University of Massachusetts Lowell
May 2023 (Expected)

BS Computer Engineering – GPA 3.56

University of Massachusetts Lowell May 2018

EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research/Teaching Assistant

Jan. 2019 – Present

University of Massachusetts Lowell Energy and Combustion Research Laboratory

- * Leverages predictive models, including state-of-the-art machine learning models, to advance alternative fuel research
- * Investigates methods for feature selection and hyper-parameter tuning, including random forest trees, principal component analysis, genetic algorithms and artificial bee colonies
- * Manages a team of undergraduate computer science/engineering students in tasks related to current research efforts
- * Funded by the U.S. Department of Energy under award DE-EE0008479 as part of the Co-Optimization of Fuels & Engines (Co-Optima) project

Technical Operations/DevOps Engineer

June 2018 - Jan. 2019

Valora Technologies

- * Utilized data mining techniques to extract client-specified information from legal, financial and government documents
- * Constructed data pipelines to usher client documents from intake to delivery of extracted information
- * Trained newly hired DevOps engineers in data pipelining/mining workflow configuration
- * Obtained Moderate Risk Public Trust (MRPT) Department of Justice (DoJ) security clearance

Undergraduate Research Assistant

June 2015 - May 2018

University of Massachusetts Lowell Energy and Combustion Research Laboratory

- * Optimized predictive models to predict chemical reaction properties based on molecular structure (QSAR/QSPR)
- * Implemented optimal neural network architectures to multidimensional input and output (training) data
- * Developed open source machine learning, feature extraction and hyper-parameter tuning software packages
- * Published research efforts in The Journal of Open Source Software, Fuel, and the American Society of Mechanical Engineers Internal Combustion Engine Fall Conference

SELECTED AWARDS & HONORS

1st place, Symbotic Warehouse Robot Prototyping CompetitionMay 2018Innovative Technology Solution, UMass Lowell DifferenceMaker 50K Idea ChallengeApril 20171st place, Francis College of Engineering Prototyping CompetitionDec. 2016UMass Lowell Francis College of Engineering Dean's ScholarshipSep. 2014

PUBLICATIONS & PRESENTATIONS

- P8. **Travis Kessler**, Thomas Schwartz, Hsi-Wu Wong, John Hunter Mack. "Screening Compounds for Fast Pyrolysis and Catalytic Biofuel Upgrading Using Artificial Neural Networks". *ASME Internal Combustion Engine Division Fall Technical Conference* (2019). https://doi.org/10.1115/ICEF2019-7170
- P7. Sanskriti Sharma, Hernan Gelaf-Romer, **Travis Kessler**, John Hunter Mack. "ECabc: A feature tuning program focused on Artificial Neural Network hyperparameters". *Journal of Open Source Software* (2019). https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.01420
- P6. John Hunter Mack, **Travis Kessler**. "A Computational Approach to Screening Alternative Fuel Candidates". *New England Energy Research Forum* (2019).
- P5. **Travis Kessler**, Eric Sacia, Alexis Bell, John Hunter Mack. "Artificial neural network based predictions of cetane number for furanic biofuel additives". *Fuel*, 206, 171-179 (2017). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fuel.2017.06.015
- P4 **Travis Kessler**, Gregory Dorian, John Hunter Mack. "Application of a Rectified Linear Unit (ReLU) Based Artificial Neural Network to Cetane Number Predictions". *ASME Internal Combustion Engine Division Fall Technical Conference* (2017). https://doi.org/10.1115/icef2017-3614
- P3. **Travis Kessler**, John Hunter Mack. "ECNet: Large scale machine learning projects for fuel property prediction". *Journal of Open Source Software* (2017). https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.00401
- P2. **Travis Kessler**, Eric Sacia, Alexis Bell, John Hunter Mack. "Predicting the Cetane Number of Furanic Biofuel Candidates Using an Improved Artificial Neural Network Based on Molecular Structure". *ASME Internal Combustion Engine Division Fall Technical Conference* (2016). https://doi.org/10.1115/icef2016-9383
- P1. **Travis Kessler**, John Hunter Mack. "Predicting Biofuel Properties with an Artificial Neural Network". *UMass Lowell Student Research and Engagement Symposium* (2016).

TECHNICAL COMMUNICATIONS

Google Scholar: <u>Travis Kessler</u>

GitHub: https://github.com/tjkessler

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/traviskessler/